and kind of the confluence of this whole idea of the Confluence Week, the merging of two
rivers.
And as we've kind of seen recently in politics and in the world, there's a lot of situations
where water is very important right now, and it's a very big issue.
So that is the reason that the back of the logo is considered water.
So let me see the creation of the logo here.
So that basically kind of sums up the reason behind the logo and all the meanings behind
the symbolism.
And you'll hear a little bit more about our Confluence Week as basically highlighting all
of these indigenous events and things that are happening around Denver so that we can
kind of bring more people together and kind of share this whole idea of Indigenous People's
Day.
So thank you.
Thank you so much, and thanks for your leadership.
All right.
Welcome to the Denver City Council meeting of Monday, October 9th.
Please rise with the Pledge of Allegiance by Councilman Lopez.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of the United States of America, to the republic for which
it stands, one nation under God, indivisible, with liberty and justice for all.
All right.
Thank you, Councilman Lopez.
Madam Secretary, roll call.
Black.
Clerk.
Here.
Espinosa.
Flynn.
Gilmour.
Here.
Cashman.
Kenich.
Here.
Lopez.
New.
Ortega.
Here.
Sussman.
Mr. President.
Here.
Eleven present.
Eleven members present.
We do have a quorum.
Approval of the minutes.
Are there any corrections to the minutes of October 2nd?
Seeing none.
The minutes of October 2nd stand approved.
Council announcements.
Are there any announcements by members of council?
Councilman Clark.
Thank you, Mr. President.
I just wanted to invite everyone down to the first ever Halloween parade on Broadway
in Lucky District 7.
It will happen on Saturday, October 21st at 6 o'clock p.m.
It will move along Broadway from 3rd to Alameda.
It's going to be a fun, family-friendly event.
Everyone's invited to come down, wear a costume.
There will be candy for the kids and there are tiki zombies and 29 hearses and all
kinds of fun and funky stuff on the fun and funky part of Broadway.
So please join us October 21st at 6 o'clock for the Broadway Halloween parade.
Thank you, Mr. President.
All right.
Thank you, Councilman Clark.
I will be there.
All right.
Presentations.
Madam Secretary, do we have any presentations?
None, Mr. President.
Communications.
Do we have any communications?
None, Mr. President.
We do have one proclamation this evening, Proclamation 1127, an observance of the
annual Indigenous Peoples Day in the City and County of Denver.
Councilman Lopez, will you please read it?
Thank you, Mr. President, with pride.
Proclamation number 17.
Well, let me just say this differently.
Proclamation number 1127, series of 2017, an observance of the second annual Indigenous
Peoples Day in the City and County of Denver.
Whereas the Council of the City and County of Denver recognizes that the Indigenous
Peoples have lived and flourished on the lands known as the Americas since time immemorial
and that Denver and the surrounding communities are built upon the ancestral homelands
of numerous Indigenous tribes, which include the Southern Ute, the Ute Mountain, Ute
of Colorado, and whereas the tribal homelands and seasonal encampments of the Arapaho and
Cheyenne people along the banks of the Cherry Creek and South Platte River confluence
give bearing to the future settlements that would become the birthplace of the Mile
High City.
And whereas Colorado encompasses the ancestral homelands of 48 tribes, and the City and
County of Denver and surrounding communities are home to the descendants of approximately
100 tribal nations.
And whereas, on October 3rd, 2016, the City and County of Denver unanimously passed
Council Bill 801, series of 2016, officially designating the second Monday of October
of each year as Indigenous Peoples Day in Denver, Colorado.
And whereas, the Council of the City and County of Denver continues to recognize and
value the vast contributions made to the community through Indigenous people's knowledge, science,
philosophy, arts, and culture, and through these contributions, the City of Denver has
developed and thrived.
Whereas the Indigenous community, especially youth, have made great efforts this year
to draw attention to the contributions of Indigenous people, including Confluence
Drawing record attendance to a national Indigenous youth leadership conference, leading conversations
on inclusion with their peers, and supporting increased Indigenous youth participation in
science and engineering.
Now therefore, be it proclaimed by the Council of the City and County of Denver,
Section 1, that the Council of the City and County of Denver celebrates and honours
the cultural and foundational contributions of Indigenous people to our history, our
past, our present, and future, and continues to promote the education of the Denver community
about these historic and contemporary contributions of Indigenous people.
Section 2, that the City and County of Denver, Colorado, does hereby observe October
9, 2017, as Indigenous Peoples Day.
Section 3, that the Clerk of the City and County of Denver shall attest and affix
the seal of the City and County of Denver to this proclamation, and that a copy be
transmitted to the Denver American Indian Commission, the City and County of Denver
School District Number 1, and the Colorado Commission on Indian Affairs.
Thank you, Councilman Lopez.
Your motion to adopt.
Mr. President, I move that Proclamation Number 1127, Series of 2017 be adopted.
Alright, it has been moved and seconded.
It comes to the members of Council.
Councilman Lopez.
Thank you, Mr. President.
It gives me a lot of pleasure and pride to read this proclamation officially for the
third time, but as Indigenous Peoples Day in Denver officially for the second time.
It's always awesome to be able to see not just this proclamation come by my desk,
but to see so many different people from our community in our council chambers.
It was a very beautiful piece of artwork that you presented to us earlier, and it
is exactly the spirit that we drafted this proclamation and this actual, the ordinance
that created Indigenous Peoples Day when we sat down and wrote it, and as a community,
we couldn't think of anything else to begin except for the confluence of the
two rivers.
And those confluence of the two rivers created such a great city, and we live in such an amazing
city and we're all proud of it, and sometimes we, and a lot of people from all over the
country or all over the world are proud of it, and sometimes a little too proud
of it is just telling them to go back home, but I'm kidding when I say that.
But the really nice thing about this is that we are celebrating Indigenous Peoples
Day out of pride for who we are, who we are as a city and the contributions of
Indigenous people to the city, not out of spite, not out of a replacement of one
culture over the other or out of contempt or disrespect.
You know, I think of a quote that Cesar Chavez made very popular, and it stuck
with me for a very long time, and anytime I have the opportunity to speak in front
of children and especially children in our community that, you know, they often
second-guess themselves on where they're coming from, who they are, and I always
say that, you know, it's very important to be proud of who we are from, and
the quote that I use from Cesar Chavez is, you know, pride in one's own
cultures does not require contempt or disrespect of another, right, and that's
very important. It's very important for us to recognize that, no matter who we
are, where we come from in this society, that your pride in your own culture
does not require the contempt or disrespect of another, and man, what a
year for that to just sit on our shoulders for a while, for us to
think about, right, and so I wanted to just to thank you all. I think the
Commission, there's gonna be a couple individuals that are gonna come speak.
Thank you for your art, your lovely artwork, for us to see what's in your
heart and what now has become a, probably is gonna be a very important
symbol for the community, and also just for the work, the daily work
every single day. We still have a lot of brothers and sisters whose
ancestors once lived in these lands freely now stand on street corners, right,
in poverty, without access to services, right, without access to sobriety or
even housing or jobs, and what a, what a, what a cruel way to pay back a
culture that has paved the way for the city to be built upon its shores,
right, so we have a lot of work to do, and these kind of proclamations in this day
is not a day off, it's a day on in Denver, right, and addressing those
those critical issues, so I know that my colleagues are very supportive. I'm
gonna ask you to support this proclamation, as I know you always
have done in the past. I'm very proud of today. Oh, and we made Time
Magazine and Newsweek once again today, as being a leader in terms of the cities
that are celebrating Indigenous Peoples Day. I wanted to make a point out of
that. Thank you, Councilman Lopez, and thank you for sponsoring this. Councilman
Martega? Mr. President, I want to ask that my name be added. I don't think I
could add much more to what Councilman Lopez has shared with us. I want to
thank him for bringing this forward, and really just appreciate all the
contributions that our Native American community has contributed to this great
city and great state. I worked in the Lieutenant Governor's Office when the
Commission on Indian Affairs was created and had the benefit of being
able to go down to the Four Corners for a peace treaty signing ceremony
between the Utes and the Comanches that had been sort of at odds with
each other for about a hundred years, and just being able to participate in
that powwow was pretty awesome. And for those of you who continue to
participate in the annual powwow, it's such a great opportunity for
everybody else to enjoy so many of the contributions of the culture. I
mean, to see that the dance continues to be carried on, as well as the
Native language, from generation to generation is just so incredible,
because in so many cultures, you know, people have come here and assimilated to
the, you know, the norms here and they lose their language and lose a
lot of the culture. And in the Native community, that hasn't happened.
That has, that, you know, commitment to just passing that on from generation to
generation is so important. And so I'm happy to be a co-sponsor of this
tonight. Thank you. All right, thank you, Councilwoman Artega. Councilwoman
Kenich. Thank you very much, and I also want to thank my colleague for
bringing this forward. And I just wanted to say a word to the artists about how
beautiful and moving I thought this logo was and your description of it. And I
think one of the things that is clear is, you know, the words sometimes don't
convey the power of imagery or music or the other pieces that make up
culture, and so I think the art is so important. And when you talked about
water, I was also thinking about land, and I guess I just wanted to say
thank you. Many of the Native American peoples of Colorado have been at the
forefront, or actually nationally, of defending some of the public lands that
have been protected over the last few years that are under attack right now.
And they're places that you all, the communities have fought to protect, but
that everyone gets to enjoy. And so I just think that it's an example of
where cultural preservation intersects with environmental protection, with, you
know, recreation and all of the other ways that public lands are so
important. And so I think I just wanted to say thank you for that, because I
think we have some very sacred places in our country that are at risk right
now. And so as we celebrate, I appreciate that there's still a piece
of resistance in here, and I think that I just want to mention a
solidarity, and mention a feeling of solidarity with that resistance. So
thank you, and happy Confluence Week. Thank you, Councilman Kenich, and see
no other comments. I'll just say a couple. And in a time of such divisive
ugliness and just despicable behavior from our leadership, the reason I'm so
supportive of Indigenous Peoples' Day is because it means inclusivity. It
means respecting all, respecting those who have been silenced on purpose
for a long time and whose history has not been told. And so we celebrate
inclusivity in the face of such evil times, honestly.